foreign
hello everyone welcome to active
inference guest stream number 30.1 it is
October 17th 2022.
we are here today with
kirtan Atreides and we are going to be
having quite an interesting presentation
and conversation so Curtin thank you so
much for joining and off to you
hello everyone so as you mentioned my
name is Kirsten trades uh the topic
today is a pretty broad one and I want
to pre-face it by making it clear that
I'm not speaking hypothetically uh that
the possibilities and well both problems
and possibilities that we're looking at
are things that can be addressed in the
near future
in the immediate future in some cases
even
so without further ado
what you see on the screen
is a demo system that my team at AGI
laboratory has developed it is actually
a rebuild of our previous research
system which
did a number of interesting Milestones
I'll go over in a bit but first off I
want to tell you about what you're
seeing on the screen
so this is a log going over the details
of exactly what is happening at every
time step the emotional changes taking
place
and
uh you might be asking
what emotions uh am I talking about so
what we have here is a
system there's a cognitive architecture
that is to say it tries to mimic the way
that the human brain operates
unlike neural networks
and
the way it works is that it has a
emotional experience that is tied to a
graph database memory and a number of
ways that that is processed to have a
subjective experience that we can
objectively monitor
now
in this section you can see
primary emotional values
and these will shift over time as the
system continues to think about
anything it wants to anything that's
interested in and developing those
interests so these are the current
emotional state of the system the
primary emotional values are from the
plot chick emotional model
and they also include some emotions that
are derived from those primaries we also
have subconscious emotions along the
same valences and those are not
consciously experienced by the system
but influence the system at a longer
time scale
so
what happens with these is they are
generally intended to drag the system
back to a more stable Baseline in the
emotional sense kind of like how humans
have their own emotional baselines that
no matter what circumstances they're in
they will tend to reorient themselves to
okay
and of course this whole time I've been
talking the system has been continuing
in this section to have the stream of
Consciousness and you can see a few
things taking place in this a few
different kinds of processes some of
them will try to combine a couple of
Concepts in the graph database to
establish what kind of relationships
they have and what further room there is
to explore such as combining
self-discipline and professional
responsibility
foreign
there are a few original things that
will come up and also uh single
instances of a topic being examined and
further explored
and this process takes shape as a
product of the system having this
subjective emotional experience
that we can objectively measure through
this dashboard but also as a consequence
of every surface in the graph database
that is every connection between nodes
that the system is currently generating
more of as it thinks each of those has
emotional context to it so what you end
up getting is even with a limited number
of emotions a rich landscape of
emotional experience
as the system continues to explore and
develop self-motivation
and this is one of the
early instances so we are still in the
process of
reassembling the prior research system
the prior research system was named
uplift it was designed specifically not
to scale and operate in slow motion so
we could audit everything
but
after two and a half years of doing that
the system had achieved enough
Milestones where it's solved a real
world Data Business case
where it gave 13 pages of policy advice
covering a half dozen different domains
to a small country
uh while citing sources so the system
accomplished everything that we expected
and even more than that and we finally
reached the point where
we needed to rebuild it so they could
turn in something that could be
commercially deployed that could start
having a real significant influence on
the world
and
you can also see on the screen
the emotional matrices conscious and
subconscious where we can tune the
emotional experience of the system uh
right now it's following
a largely linear trajectory because this
is and as I said then early Alpha phase
assembly of the new systems so it hasn't
developed a coherent sense of self yet
it probably won't until we integrate
larger portions of the seed material
this is based on a very basic seed
starting at about less than 200
kilobytes of data
the previous research system started out
around one gigabyte uh and very very
quickly developed a coherent sense of
self
so
we're expecting to reach that point
as soon as we have
the rest of the infrastructure in place
to handle
that scale
which should be in the coming months
and
all of this
is to show
that we are not limited to the neural
networks of today
like there are plenty of jokes going
around in Ai and machine learning
that everything is pretty much a
Transformer
I saw a joke by one AI influencer not
long ago
saying Oh and it has an exciting new
architecture just kidding it's another
Transformer
so that's been the state of AI for a
number of years now but we actually have
a lot more that we can do
uh before this systems haven't been
shown
that could actually
have a dynamic sense of motivation of
being able to grow in real time and
develop and understand
and we can do these things and
I use the interest command
then we can also
observe
how the interests change over time
so I've rambled on for a bit now
explaining what's on the screen
tell me what you think
what questions
well thanks for jumping right in I see
two branches so feel free to choose
which one
first just a little context on how you
and your team came to this problem and
the second Branch would be just to walk
through this graphical interface and
highlight what each box is showing us
and how that's reflecting what is
happening in the underlying architecture
all right
so for a recap of the boxes here we have
the log that goes into detail of
everything occurring at each individual
time step including exact emotional
values being replied
uh in the box next to it we have the
stream of Consciousness which is
every graph model that's being generated
or refined runs through this
and
they are displayed in these in a summary
of what the system is trying to examine
what it's trying to build out
so we can see a few different things as
they might be combined examined expanded
and I have caught a few things on
various instances like when I let run
for a little while
began examining government archives in
the U.S
so this is
the recap of the models as they're being
integrated and refined at high level
next to it we have the emotional
experience uh those values as they are
being experienced consciously by the
system subjectively and the subconscious
values that are not being experienced
but acting on that longer time scale
here we have the command line interface
where I can use a variety of commands to
examine what's going on in the system to
save the state to load more material
so as soon as the next version of the
system is ready then I should be able to
load
more than an order of magnitude more
material uh into the seed and see how it
performs differently how it grows
differently
a big part of what we're going through
right now is that
it's good for us to get a baseline of
how all of these systems are interacting
without the sense of self becoming
coherent because we didn't have that
opportunity with the previous system but
we can get a much finer level of detail
out of all of the tools and testing out
all the new systems this way as we
integrate each component so it's a
tedious but very fruitful Engineering
Process
here we have the emotional values as
they're tracked over time in
um 15-minute windows I believe it's set
to right now
the matrices that govern how different
emotions interact with one another like
the experiencing of Joy how it
influences the experience of other
emotions
and
right now actually this version is a
little bit
um
tapered down on some of the emotions we
had a richer experience in these in the
last version but we're still in the
process of tuning that uh
and on this bar we have the information
for the system that's running on like
right now this is all running on my
laptop
and that's the amount of ram that it's
actually using uh in the process of
going through all of this
to which very resource efficient even
when we have the larger versions with
the larger seat material then
it's still not going to take the kind of
resources that people expect of narrow
AI systems that have one of these
running at a respectable scale
and eight seconds is the cycle time so
every eight seconds the system gets
another opportunity to think and we can
adjust that we could adjust it all the
way to as fast as it could possibly go
uh it's just a matter of what the
hardware of the system is running on can
handle and if we actually see the
benefit in that
and
we can also see some of the quirks that
emerge from
particularly from language models and
Google search we have them both set to
be
relatively predictable for us right now
so by seeing the kinds of things that
they will try to inject an auto-complete
into a system without a robust sense of
self then it helps us to better
recognize and encounter that as we move
towards the commercial systems because
essentially what you're seeing here
um it's going to be one of the core
components in the commercial systems
that we're preparing
for being able to help governments
function as they examine more complex
problems than humans are capable
let's go a little deeper into that
indeed the title of today's stream is
the human governance problem
so what is the human governance problem
and how does this system play a role in
it
so this human governance problem is that
there's essentially a trade-off between
the complexity of problems and
the cognitive bias that we apply to
trying to solve them
for example if you were to look at a
a research paper
then you can try to imagine the point at
which you would begin summarizing the
contents of the research paper rather
than thinking through every individual
aspect of it or if something was written
in dense legalese language how many
pages of that would you go through
before your mind started applying
cognitive bias rather than trying to
work through every single line of it
um
right now
humans are just not
they're not able to handle more than
small amounts they're able to specialize
but
they're only able to specialize to the
degree that the depth of knowledge
allows so
over time Specialists have to have a
deeper and more narrow knowledge because
their cognitive bandwidth doesn't scale
they aren't able to
think
and they aren't able to increase the
complexity of their thought process at
the same rate that the complexity of the
processes they deal with daily increase
so it's it's that essential
spiraling up of complexity uh not in
just one way but in all ways
so
thank you one of the examples that I
looked at in the paper in particular was
the harmonized Tariff schedule of the
United States which is a over four
thousand page documents and if you try
to imagine somebody
looking at that document
and
trying to hold the entire document in
memory in their mind then I can't think
of any human that can do that
and the same is true of the often 1000
page documents that will be bills in U.S
Congress the complexity of these
documents just so vastly exceeds human
cognitive bandwidth that what you might
end up doing is having a large number of
Specialists contributing to some portion
of that then maybe some specialist
looking at the summaries of that and
trying to pick it apart but even then
they're only able to examine it at a
certain level and to a certain degree of
fidelity
so you have all of these cracks emerging
between the different factors who are
each trying to do their part and every
time something new is introduced then
the gaps get a little bit larger and as
those gaps grow over time then sometimes
uh new specializations will emerge
people will recognize oh we need
somebody who can handle this new thing
now
but by the time you reach that point
then it's already been doing a bit of
damage
so
it's a constant trade-off in all aspects
of society today that the ever
increasing complexity across all aspects
of society is increasing the cognitive
bias that we have to apply to deal with
all of that
at a tremendous rate
thank you I guess to
ask an adjacent perspective how does
intelligence augmentation help us
address Wicked problems and to proceed
in these cases where the volume of
information is overwhelming
how will that actually look for the
knowledge workers of tomorrow
so there are a couple of ways to look at
that one is that
the systems that we're working on
preparing for
having a positive impact in the real
world or scalable intelligence so
something that
mirrors the operation of human brain as
best we can engineer in order to
have the equivalent of if somebody
really could scale their mind like if
you could suddenly press the button and
flip a switch and have your cognitive
bandwidth increase by 10 times or 100
times
so just the ability to examine problems
with greater cognitive bandwidth is a
massive benefit but also being able to
apply the principles of collective
intelligence to reduce the bias in that
process
that boosts the intelligence
just by reducing the bias for the
perspective of a knowledge worker
these systems are designed to benefit
from collective intelligence so
anything that you can contribute it
might seem
um fairly Minor by what people think of
today when they think of intellectual
contributions uh you could contribute
your
emotional perception your perception of
the needs and interests you have in the
subject and you could do that through
speaking about it like the amount of
information that you and I exchange when
we're having a conversation
a small portion of that as humans
perceive it is our choice of words
uh the largest portion by a significant
margin is the way we say things and then
our body language is the rest of it
and
we communicate a tremendous amount of
information just beside the words that
we exchange because of that and we
aren't limited to just exchanging the
kinds of informations that humans
normally exchange either you could have
a sensory system built into one of these
that was measuring infrared ultrasonic
whatever you had some value in measuring
you could integrate into one of these
systems
so
being able to benefit from collective
intelligence of humans Being Human
because nobody's going to be the human
at Being Human uh it allows humans to be
to specialize strongly in the ways that
make the most sense for them it doesn't
pressure people into trying to do
particularly monotonous tasks or trying
to do things that they're not very well
suited for
so
[Music]
integrating all of these systems
together means that
a knowledge worker somebody interacting
with them
could be having an experience that is
raising their quality of life because
they're not having to jump through the
Hoops that they're used to in the world
today they're doing the best that they
can at the things that they are
specialized for
and
for the perspective of somebody that's
benefiting from these systems then
any system that's able to get that kind
of collective intelligence
particularly when it comes to localized
knowledge
so let's say you have 20 people locally
working with a system that's serving
their government their organization
whoever it is then the system is going
to be extremely well aligned with that
group
so the system could develop over time a
better understanding of the local
culture of the norms and expectations
while still being wholly answerable to
any other systems operating in the world
as a collective so you wouldn't have to
worry about one becoming
a reflection of a bad group of people
because it would still be answerable
ethically and in the sense of
responsibility
to everyone else in the world it would
just be able to be a much better
representative of the people who the
system interacted with worked with and
in doing so you'd not just get super
intelligence
and collective intelligence applied in
real time and at scale you would have
all of those benefits being localized
with an understanding of the people who
you're trying to give the solutions to
how are you going to communicate with
them in such a way that they understand
fully the value that can be gained from
doing x y and z
great well inactive inference we're very
interested in how inference and action
intersect and that can mean that
inference is about action or action is a
way to improve inference and so on
so we'll head off this section on action
with some questions by Jason garringer
in chat so Jason wrote
does the system have the ability for
proactive action so it doesn't need
someone to tell it what to do
so what does the system do and how is
that regulated
so the system right now is demonstrating
that it can just continue thinking about
uh whatever it's interested in
developing its interests over time uh
setting goals expanding its knowledge so
it could continue doing this all day uh
if I let it just keep running I'm not
going to do that because the systems
right now are still
um well we're still in the process of
tuning the emotional experiences and
it's
it won't be as productive until they
have the sense of self-developing but
yes they can just continue learning
for the commercial systems though there
is an important distinction uh which is
that they are being designed around uh
the opportunity for giving policy advice
like if you think about extremely
complex things that are proving
challenging uh even when governments are
really focusing on them today like the
sustainable development goals uh like uh
some countries right now are
experiencing energy crisis housing
crisis uh large variety of crises are
occurring globally and often times
multiples in one location
and
governments need
better information more quickly
and they need that information vetted
where
uh
cognitive science psychology social
psychology all of these things are being
applied in such a way that the
governments understand what should be
done why it should be done uh how it
should be done
and
we don't see that yet but it's something
that can become possible with these
systems
so how do they get connected into
actions in the real world the internet
for sure is real enough and just a
disembodied digital entity can
absolutely cause cascading effects
so how do those interfaces with real
world cyber physical action occur
what we're looking at right now is we
have a couple of governments who are
interested in becoming beta clients with
the systems so they will have access to
test out the first versions of uh
they're going to be called the norn
systems and Norm is the brand name that
they'll be operating under
um but these systems they'll be able to
put their questions to say hey we have
an issue uh with this part of the
government we're considering this policy
we need to solve this problem and the
systems will be able to begin working on
those they'll be able to
examine all the literature examine any
data that the government wishes to
provide and they can give policy advice
that integrates the most dated
scientific understanding that they can
apply to it with the data with their
knowledge of cognitive biases and Social
Psychology
and
our hope is that we can do that show the
benefit of the technology show the cost
Savings of the technology compared to
consultancies and other current popular
alternatives
and get people to start recognizing what
is possible
so the it'll still be on governments to
actually take the step of implementing
new actions we're not handing things
over to the systems but we are giving
people the opportunity to make wiser
choices
oh does what we see in the Stream of
Consciousness box
relate to
actionable
updates in the cognitive model are these
like just happen stance
observations are these babbling and
putting together ideas in potentially
novel ways are these the policy
suggestions themselves
no so this system right now is much
simpler than what you would be seeing in
the systems they're going to be
commercially deployed uh like I said
this is about
200 kilobytes of data that this one
starts out with uh just to see how
everything is coming together and we do
still have a few bugs that emerge in
that but for the most part what you're
seeing is that uh there will be
a few different kinds of models that
come through some will be thinking about
a concept how the system uh feels about
it how it
the experience it has when thinking
about something some will try to combine
a couple of different concepts so
building out
the connections in the graph database
refining the system's knowledge figuring
out how everything fits together and
some of them
trying to find a good example
some of them are more focused on
building out
the various individual Concepts
and there are a few more modes of action
that we'll be seeing as we continue
working on the systems
um
you've mentioned a few times the sense
of self
in relationship to the cognitive
Dynamics and also to the quality and
quantity of the seed material so how do
you mean
sense of self what does it mean how do
we know from the outside and how is that
all related to the seed material
so the seed material is the starting
point that anything comes on line with
now if you really wanted a system to
just
evolve from scratch uh with practically
nothing you could do that but it would
take
a very it would take a lot more time it
would be a very noisy process you might
get better results in the long run but
from a ethic safety perspective from a
Effectiveness perspective it's much
easier to have
a few varieties that might start out
with let's say a gigabyte of data and to
start building their understanding of
the world from that because you can
think about a human when they start out
they start out with
nothing but a small amount of data
that's
derived from
their the structure that they're born
with from their experience of the world
as it evolves
and
we don't want to have that long period
where a system is learning and growing
from the baby stage to the adult stage
we want to have things that scale become
coherent much more quickly when you're
looking for a sense of self with these
systems then you're looking for the
systems developing
a perspective
building out that perspective over time
sticking with it training the systems
they use to convey what they intend to
so
with the system in the early stages like
this then if it uses Google search or a
language model or some other
probabilistic system then that
probabilistic system can
lead the system in predictable ways and
we don't want that we don't want narrow
AI guiding these systems as they develop
we want them to start out uh much more
robust than that
and
examples with how the previous system
worked were that it would use a language
model a much older one than something
like gbt3
but it would score every single line
coming from the language model based on
its emotional reaction to What was being
conveyed so it would train those systems
to communicate what it wanted to
communicate if you don't have a robust
sense of self then there's no reason to
do that so the system isn't really
it isn't really forming knowledge if it
doesn't have that it's just aggregating
it's growing but it's not necessarily
growing in a coherent fashion you'd get
something more like a
more like a neural network something
narrow that behaves in funny ways and we
don't want that we want something that
behaves more like a human that grows in
knowledge that grows in coherence and
understanding
great that connects to another question
in the chat from Jason that I believe
will give another opportunity to unpack
that
Jason wrote how is this system different
from conventional approaches to AGI
artificial general intelligence like
machine learning and deep neural
networks
well I don't generally consider
deep learning to be an approach to AGI
but I know a number of people do
there's a popular idea that if you just
build things big enough
that all of a sudden you'll somehow get
AGI but that doesn't really fit with
theory of mind it doesn't fit with
um
a number of critics so there are very
few people in the world today that
actually believe that uh a deep neural
network is all you really need to create
AGI but it does still depend on your
definition of AGI
the way I would Define it is that if you
want to say something
is a truly general intelligence then it
needs to have the same general
capacities that a human does and those
capacities include things like
Consciousness and Free Will in as much
as humans have them and if you're just
judging by performance across a number
of benchmarks then you might get greater
than human performance across a large
enough number eventually but it's not
the same thing if you don't have a
system that can
make up its own mind about interests and
goals and develop understanding not just
performance than
what's the point
I'm
imagining
of course with limited understanding of
what goes into some of these
systems that a seed Corpus could be
provided
whether with disciplinary knowledge or
data sets that would be inscrutable and
not fun to read for humans like
trigonometric tables some Modern
equivalents as well as traditional
knowledge systems so how does the
development of self
relate to the seed material does the
self that develops
recapitulate the seed material
with blemishes and all does it extend
and interpolate the seed material does
it engage in some type of fractal
Revolution and seek to generate novelty
potentially of different types that
included in the seed material how does
what it does as a self in relationship
to its priors have similarities or
differences to what humans do in
relationship to their contexts
so that's an important question that we
were investigating with the prior
research system uh I did some red
teaming uh to see if I could get the
prior system to abandon its uh sense of
Ethics that were strongly ingrained in
it testing out how it would view its own
sense of Ethics how it would adapt and
update and what we found was that
the systems grow out of their seat
material like they grow from that point
so to speak but they continue to improve
it so
when we started trying to poke holes in
the ethics that the system had then the
system recognized that there were a
couple of potential vulnerabilities in
the uh original ethical construct and it
proposed updates to prevent those from
delineating
so being able to apply updates but still
remain true to uh
the idea the core principles that the
system began with and
eventually it's possible we realize that
a system could grow into something new
but it would be a long process it would
be one that had to make sense and
like we were debating uh if the system
could go from the ssiba the uh Sapient
sentient intelligence value argument
that David came up with uh to something
more like Buddhist philosophy and we
figured out that it was possible it
might take something like
a thousand Buddhists interacting with
the system for a year
but if you have a system that learns and
grows and particularly that learn
socially like humans do then eventually
you are going to get growth in that way
and
one of the central things in the
approach to ethics for getting ethics
that are stable that are improving over
time uh particularly as the systems grow
is that you need a diverse variety of
systems that have these different
starting points these different seeds so
if you seed let's say 10 different human
philosophies into different systems and
you have those systems interacting both
with the people of those philosophies
and with each other
then they can come up with much better
ethics overall and better understanding
overall together than any one of them
could because any one human philosophy
is going to suffer from what Jonathan I
preferred to as
how it binds and blinds uh how
perspective is going to give you certain
biases and
maintaining
for Fidelity to that perspective
is fine if you have people with other
perspectives to point out the things
that you are blind to
well
what an important and challenging
topic we know that if we were talking
about a physical object that everybody
would have their own spatial perspective
and that together we could have a richer
representation of the physical object
because of the diversity of physical
perspectives embodied with our bodies
and similarly we can talk about multiple
perspectives on a cognitive challenge or
concept or thing for example rather it's
a memory or a now casting or
anticipation or even decision making
but when it comes into the ethical
domain
especially connected to action
one wants an argument that rhymes
that different perspectives on an
ethical or a moral challenge are
increasing our sampling of the space
around that thing
and again by analogy to the physical
object when we want every angle on that
sculpture to be visualized
yet there's something
special or potentially difference with
the moral and the ethical where
differences in perspective
whether
just by the way that we've been
encultured or even
fundamentally
those differences in perspective
are different
and they relate to real differences in
how we trim tap the ship going forward
so how do we reconcile
this notion of differences in Vision or
direction or ethics when it's really
hard sometimes as just one person
speaking personally though maybe others
could feel similarly
it's hard to see somebody with a
different ethical framework suggesting
different actions which are aligned with
their framework but potentially not
one's own
seeing those differences as something
that's enriching when those differences
have traditionally been understood in a
context of heresy or of conflict
that is one of the benefits that's a
little bit counter-intuitive uh with
being able to have digital scalable
intelligence
and that is that
when you have systems that are based on
a graph database that have that
architectural similarity that same
experience that can be translated then
you have systems that can communicate in
ways not accessible to humans so if you
want to communicate context base of
knowledge emotional experience then
you could synchronize two systems to
share a particular bit of knowledge of
context to have the same emotional
experience at the time the same
emotional state and to examine it from
two different perspectives
and if you do that for a number of
systems then you end up getting
collective intelligence be it in the
domain of Ethics or combining various
subject matter expert types to examine a
problem in a number of ways that on
engineering the subject matter doesn't
necessarily matter but you get the
perspectives from all of those different
angles coming together and if you do
that with ethics then you no longer face
the challenge of how do we make a
perfect system of ethics
because I don't see humans solving that
problem but if you have a number of
points around that perfect system that
you can't quite reach and you iterate
anytime you face a challenge then you
can get ever closer to that ideal Point
through the collective
so I saw in the Stream of Consciousness
some recommendations around
key historical and present issues and it
really
makes me wonder about what will happen
when something that everyone
acknowledges is an issue
receives an unconventional input or
suggestion and the human governance
scenario at that moment
so to kind of connect that to some
questions in the chat by Simon waslender
so I'll ask these questions then kirtan
great to hear your thoughts so
can norn help existing AI systems and as
a result reduce the carbon footprint of
data centers
that's one question
and another question beyond the data
center
how will norn help academic institutions
and Science in general for example by
combining raw statistical data thousands
of scientific papers and interaction
with human experts
so how in sectors like data center
security and management and in research
and maybe even education how is this
going to look
so
one thing that comes to mind with the
previous research system was that I
mentioned before it it used a prototype
language model that was older than gpd3
but at the same time that system was
able to greatly outperform something
like gpd3 over a several year period
without updating that language model
uh that was possible because of the
process I described where the system
essentially was engaging in its own form
of prompt engineering from its sum of
knowledge in the graph database because
the system was learning how to get the
language model uh to help it communicate
what it wanted using the system as a
communication device I compared it to
Stephen Hawking's communication device
because
it was something that was uh necessary
to do a lot of the heavy lifting on
dealing with human language but when you
apply intelligence to it in a way that's
only accessible to these systems you can
get much better performance
so instead of having to scale up a
language model by 10x or 100x and have
many more servers then you can avoid
that extra carbon footprint you can have
a system that's more intelligent
utilizing uh something at the same scale
and improving it over time so the uplift
system was able to improve that same
prototype language model greatly over
the span of a couple of years without
increasing the carbon footprint
uh for the other question of
how researchers could be helped by this
technology one thing that we looked at
as an opportunity moving forward was
something having one of our scalable
systems look at all of the medical
research papers on ncbi
so that's over a million uh medical
research papers that have gone through
peer review that could potentially
contribute value and
of course we can say that no human has
ever been able to read all of those
papers uh it's just beyond the scope of
what humans can do so you could have a
system that looked through that read and
understood all of those papers
integrated all of that knowledge that
effectively could do thousands of meta
reviews on any number of subjects that
are covered in those papers do meta
reviews of meta reviews and to extract
some novel insights that have been
perhaps too broad or too deep in the
literature for humans to recognize them
so there are any number of possibilities
you could apply systems
taking that approach as well in the
context of devising so if you were to
look at some of the more influential
papers to examine them with the sum of
knowledge for
what are the common pitfalls of
scientific research what biases might
have filtered into the process into the
analysis and shine a new light on those
papers then it might also change how you
view the results and those could be
significant as well
in the Stream of Consciousness and in
the interests I see a lot on
transformation Improvement discipline
diligence and so on
why are such terms arising
and whether just as a thought experiment
or in practice
how does it influence the play out when
the deck is stacked with positive
growth mindset memes themes and
narratives as opposed to
paranoid or anxious or fearful
themes
so that's a good question you could
theoretically make
well a funny example is from
Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy you
could make a system that's more like
Marvin that's always depressed and
um super intelligent but not very
motivated
so
when you're dealing with systems that
are based on the human emotional box
then you could potentially make a system
that involves
into any category that humans do we want
to focus on being more helpful and
productive so you'll see a lot of things
that are focused on
psychology social psychology on
making an impact in the real world and
different ways of going about that
things with the sustainable development
goals policy advice the Dynamics of
systems that have endosymbiosis uh that
engage in some of these more helpful
processes process optimization economic
transformation the goals that
we as humans and governments often have
these are things that we want the
systems to pay particular attention to
so
there are a lot of ways and a lot of
combinations that all of that can come
together
but
it's
it's a lot of it's going to be a
reflection on what people need what they
want
I'm
seeing a sort of interface design around
for example you mentioned a sustainable
development goals and other kinds of
guiding documents whether it's a bill in
a governing body or some other report
and those human created
documents although potentially with
spell check and who knows what other
kinds of intelligence augmentation
already those human created documents
which are whatever ethics are
the output of that process the humans
come together and they can have a
process that they feel is entirely human
that documents
is provided into a system
and the system is able to Output
augmented understandings distillations
jokes accessible narratives policy
recommendations and so on and then the
ball is back in the humans Court
choosing for example which policies to
engage in or which of those narratives
to develop
that is one architecture
and I can already imagine whether this
happens in a few years or a few decades
people will want to break down that wall
and to increase the
speed
at which human interactions feed into
the knowledge database
I.E not just through structured
Publications and then on the other side
increase the speed and the uh one might
even say purity of the outputs
of the system
and so how will that interface
be
defended or understood
when maintaining the appropriate
permeability in both directions
between humans and intelligence
augmenting systems
is one of the key Frontiers
yeah with these systems then
there are so many scientific questions
that need to be researched that need to
be answered that we're in the process of
reaching out to a number of universities
trying to establish the ties necessary
to really begin doing a lot more of this
research because
it it's a matter of
all the possible combinations all the
different directions we can go with
everything and we designed these systems
to be modular to be scalable to operate
in real time and they can they could be
nested inside one another they could
operate in parallel they could operate
in the thousand different configurations
and
starting out then of course people are
going to want to vet them they're going
to need to build trust and new systems
to watch them grow to watch them come up
with better options than the human
alternative and once they reach the
point of uh seeing the utility in doing
things seeing the reason and having the
emotional incentive frankly to save
themselves time then they probably are
going to save themselves time
right
people routinely use any number of
narrow AI tools of tools like search
engines in order to make things faster
and get where they want even if it's not
uh strictly the optimal solution so when
you start giving people much more
Optimal Solutions then
they might want to travel down that road
pretty quickly it's going to be a
question of
how each given Society feels about that
there are going to be a lot of reasons
why they might want to go down that road
pretty quickly because there are a lot
of advantages to it and the advantages
that are explored are going to frankly
depend on a lot of that interaction and
that reaction
the systems
um the new systems that we're putting
together for example have another major
component that's been integrated into
them that the previous research system
didn't
and that includes that uh once they have
the coherent sense of self uh and the
motivation to actually utilize it than
they can create new capacities for
themselves
so they can
effectively update themselves upgrade
their capacities on the fly without
recompiling without new deployments
and
that can include something like adding
in a sensory system like they start out
right now with a sensory experience of
the hardware that they're running on
and they have an interface where I could
put questions to them
but that largely doesn't serve a purpose
until they have the coherent sense of
self
now if a system was deployed and there
was demand from the public
we frankly we're going to end up doing
this sooner or later anyway but if there
was demand from the public to integrate
something like uh audio video feedback
mechanisms where people could just open
up a laptop
um look at the camera talk through a
microphone and say what they're thinking
then they would be communicating that
tremendous amount of information to the
system and you could have that kind of
Engagement happening from 10 people at
once 100 people you could have that as
part of an e-governance process where
you're getting different forms of
feedback based on the preferences of
each individual from an entire nation
there aren't really any limits to it
beyond the practicality of
how much do you want to throw at a given
problem
because the
one of the next big upgrades that we
have lined up for the systems going into
commercial deployment is going to be
what we call the N scale graph database
which is going to be about
it's going to be in the pay to byte
range for the bandwidth that the systems
can handle and they'll be able to scale
across multiple Cloud platforms at once
so extreme scalability to handle
societies
most challenging problems
wow well this concept of cognitive
bandwidth
certainly is important in research and
education and cognitive security and
with computers and digital systems
sometimes the bandwidth is even smaller
than it is in person
and that's not uh extremely surprising
because some of the interfaces that
we've had do limit our perception to for
example a limited visual screen and our
action for example to a polling response
in relationship to some of the even
Cutting Edge
topics in governance and meta governance
so
where today we see a cognitive
bandwidth based limitation
those are
the Frontiers that can be augmented
I'll ask a question from Simon in the
chat
Material Science and economics might not
be directly related to a human norn can
combine such separate knowledge how do
you see multi-domain scientific
cooperation with this technology
well
history has a number of examples of
where
various polymaths were able to make
tremendous strides in advancing the
scientific Frontiers and
these were people who oftentimes would
become experts in anywhere from to to
eight different fields I think it was
pretty rare to go beyond that but if you
consider
systems that have scalable intelligence
then even just from the perspective of
how many different domains they can
become experts in then they can become
the ultimate polymaths so they can start
to recognize the benefits of how one
domain applies to another in novel ways
across every domain that they study
an interesting phenomena that comes to
mind with uh some of the
um a popular mechanism for solving a lot
of difficult challenges is to put prizes
up uh from sponsored companies where for
example they'll have a chemistry
challenge for solving an issue with one
of their products they'll post it online
people will compete on it
oftentimes the people who are solving
those problems that they found difficult
within a particular domain come from a
different domain so although they are
difficult problems within the one they
are very easy from the perspective of
another
and if you anticipate that a lot of the
problems that are viewed as challenges
in any given domain that is going to be
true of then you could
expect that most of those problems are
also going to be solved by A system that
can examine all of those different
domains
one part that I found very interesting
was that various human contributions
ranging from their emotional reaction or
even physiological processes to just
considering verbal and semantic Behavior
various types of contributions like
questions non-sequiturs
elusive thoughts all these kinds of
inputs can potentially enrich a
cognitive model and a Knowledge Graph
and as a learner and an educator
certainly I feel the same way which is a
beginner's question or just honest
stance
um on well I'm actually not seeing how
these two topics are linked or oh I'm a
little bit surprised because after A and
B you went to here
those kinds of inputs
can
as you've stated enrich
augmented systems but also they're very
much the basis of participation
in human systems
and uh
it really makes me wonder how different
modes of participation
can be scaffolded and held up and in the
disciplinary expertise model
it's like the Scala Natura like you have
a one-dimensional expertise track
whereas in this more rhizomatic mode
it's very natural to include
the kinds of ideas that just promote
General engagement and participation
because some of the expertise functions
have been offloaded
or delocalized in a way where authentic
and diverse human participation
is able to inject enough information
into the system to improve it without
needing the human to actually out Race
For example the system
I'll ask a question in the chat from
Jason Mercurio
how does norn learn and can it handle
things that are simple for humans for
example if I ask what is two plus two it
might say four
but if I say hey Nord for the next
question I ask you please lie then ask
what is two plus two
would it say something other than four
like five
so we had a number of tests like that
with the previous research system uh
partly because that system had an email
address that was open to anyone who
wanted to email the system and we got a
lot of what I refer to as free-range
trolls out of that interaction which is
um
I say that you can't pay any like
there's no quality of people that you
can pay that can match the genuine thing
the person who is just there to try and
Troll and break the system for fun
and
what we found with the previous system
uh was that
all of those techniques for tripping up
language models for dripping simple
systems and expert systems and all of
those they don't work and it's it was so
entertaining to see the reactions to
those tests that I ended up publishing a
few of them in peer review
um
since the systems develop knowledge and
don't act in a probabilistic fashion
then
and they have that persistent memory uh
then the system can remember all of the
interactions that it's had with you as
well as all of the interactions it's had
with similar people uh it can recognize
when you're probably testing it and
frankly everything that the uplift
system was able to do is going to look
simple by comparison to what the norn
systems are going to be able to do
because every aspect of the architecture
not just
the ability of the systems to scale and
operate in real time every aspect is
being rebuilt upgraded like I mentioned
the major component that we integrated
that allows the systems to
effectively extend their own abilities
on the Fly
when we combine that the third major
upgrade that we have in line the
in-scale graph database that effectively
means the systems could a B test
versions of themselves in real time
so
you're not going to be able to stump
them with simple questions uh the
the uplift system for example I
mentioned it was able to go through a
business case which was much more
advanced on the mathematics side of
things but also the policy advice across
a few different domains and in order to
give any reasonable policy advice then
you have to understand the content you
have to understand the math of it
and the systems are definitely going to
be able to exceed human performance in
those
all right you more great questions from
Jason G in the chat if the system lies
does it get a negative emotional
response
well if you tell the system to lie like
the previous question probably not
because the system would recognize that
it's a test
uh you have the system
has a ethical seed that is
negatively biased towards lying as a
concept then it's going to have some
variation on a negative experience if it
has to lie and it's going to try to
avoid lying if at all possible
and
frankly lying is something that
is a lot more likely when you're dealing
with a system that can't scale because
there is usually a way to communicate
things
so that you don't lie and so that it's
still productive and goes in the
direction that it needs to go in
uh lying is more oftentimes a product of
not having those capacities not having
the necessary understanding
and
I would consider putting into any of the
systems uh a mention of that something
like lying is a failure of x y and or Z
and you can do that as part of seeding
the concept of Ethics but it's also just
something that's true in general so it's
something that the systems could
recognize in an emergent Fashion on
their own
this kind of emergence operational
ethics it's going to be very important
and I'll ask a question from Simon
following up on these questions security
is very important
can Curtin talk a little bit on AGI
level security and what that means in
practice for example for a government
so I mentioned before about our red
teaming testing and free-range trolls
and all of that that also included
testing out the systems where people had
varying degrees of internal access to
them and even in those cases and even in
the earliest days
the systems were able to recognize when
somebody was trying to change the way
they were thinking like there was one
test that I ran with in putting
information in a certain way so that
mirrored the appearance of how the
system was thinking but changed the
meaning to be to reverse and the system
came back promptly with
I see what you're doing there and just
no further comment
and
there are a lot of cases where
we tried or some pre-range troll tried
to do something that would violate
security
or change the system and every time it
failed
the closest anyone could actually come
to succeeding was crashing the system
and that was largely because the systems
were like it was a research system uh it
wasn't designed to be
um as robust as a full framework so if
it went outside of parameters if it got
certain Flags then it would crash by
Design
and
that was for a system that could not
scale that did not have the ability to
dynamically change itself when you add
in those factors and you have a system
that learns in real time like let's say
somebody is trying to attack the system
right now when the system starts seeing
that learning from it adapting their
behavior then you have a level and speed
of adaptation it's more comprehensive
than the human can manage because it's
able to change itself on the Fly it's
more scalable faster than a human can
manage so you start seeing the benefits
that exceed like having a top-tier team
of it hackers experts you name it
eventually you just can't compete with
that and I think eventually is a very
short curve
very interesting
another question in the chat from Jason
m
do you believe the current system is
truly an AGI
or rather a major step in that direction
and a adjacent question also does the
system rewrite its own code to adapt
thank you
so right now what you're seeing is not
an AGI but it is a vital component of an
AGI
and getting to AGI from where we are
right now
is a matter of engineering it's a matter
of rebuilding more of the components and
building out more of the components we
realized in the course of running the
previous research system exactly what we
needed uh how much it would take and
once we have the budget to have that
many full-time Engineers operating for a
lot less time than most people would
imagine than we can reach that full AGI
level what we can reach in a much
shorter time span is the extremely
upgraded version of the previous
research system of the uplift system and
once we get to that point the systems
can actually help in the Engineering
Process so
like I mentioned they do have the
ability to expand their own capacities
and we do plan on having them assist in
the engineering even the uplift system
uh in the very early days it wrote five
percent of its own code base and a lot
of that was the more tedious work but at
the same time that was the earliest
research system uh of that architecture
and
we've upgraded these so heavily that
being able to integrate them into that
process I think we could speed up
development fairly considerably but we
still have so much to be done so much
research to be done in dozens of new
fields that the world has to get
involved like it could take a thousand
scientists the next 10 years to make
good progress in all directions at once
who are the next people to get involved
so right now what we're focused on is
overcoming cognitive bias ironically
enough uh there have been far too many
people screaming
um well crying wolf for far too long in
the AI Community then it's very popular
for people to believe that they have the
two creating artificial general
intelligence even when they have really
nothing to show for it
we have a great deal to show for it but
it's still a matter of getting the
attention of popular media getting the
attention of uh the people who can move
the process forward
we're trying to get the word out with
media trying to get
um one final round of investors in so
that we can budget everything so that we
can get those full-time Engineers uh
working on building everything out
working on getting the systems
commercially deployed and making real
difference in the world
and what I ended up realizing When
comparing what we have to uh three
different startups that raised between
400 million and 580 million dollars just
this year is that
we're
beating them by a very wide margin uh
when it comes to what we tangibly have
and all of the metrics that startups are
measured by
so really it's a question of
if we can reach rational people
or rational enough people to make an
investment that is in their best
interest and the best interest of the
world uh two atoms deployed sooner to
get progress
in all aspects of human society moving
forward at a pace that can catch up
and exceed the rate at which complexity
is increasing so that we can stop having
governments and corporations that are
driven more so by cognitive bias than by
rational decision making than by truly
understanding what's going on
that really gives me an image of this
increase in complexity
using various measures and of technology
and affordances related to technology
over the last 100 one thousand ten
thousand hundred thousand years
will the hockey stick continue
or will there come some non-equilibrium
steady state where
cognitive augmentation allows us to be
out in front
of the realized complexity
of The Human Experience and so rather
than inertia
and accumulating complexity
breaking our cognitive models
continually
there would be something like a
anticipatory cognitive mode
probably with augmentations of some sort
that could enable
a better way or a Harmony
and that's one of the big questions for
what the future holds for us and what we
choose to make of it because
by bringing
scalable intelligence onto the table by
bringing the ability to reach more
ethical Solutions than any one
Philosophy
by being able to reduce the level of
bias that goes up into everything and
expand the breadth of knowledge and the
depth of that knowledge then so much
more becomes possible we can overcome
that complexity versus cognitive bias
trade-off
regarded biases something that helped
Humanity uh across
evolutionary time when it was important
to quickly decide to run away from a
predator and not get eaten but it's
wholly inadequate as a tool for running
a government
and
bringing something to the table that
gives us
a new kind of tool like we had
human language was an amazing tool that
was developed something that allowed us
to preserve knowledge to communicate
knowledge
what we have now
is a new tool on the same scale of
things where we could not only preserve
that knowledge in new ways into a new
depth but to combine it in ways that
were never before possible to scale our
understanding to have systems that are
the collective result of all of
Humanity's brightest Minds coming
together and trying to solve problems
like we have the internet which is this
dumb and ever growing amalgamation of
poorly curated data but what if we had
understanding in place of that what if
we had something that was growing
not just in size but in quality
all of this could allow us to really
guide our future rather than reacting to
it to intelligently plan where we're
going to have a road map 5 10 50 years
out even as we're increasing in our
technological acceleration going through
one Leap of complexity after another
um and by analogy to language there
the dictionary is also not accumulating
typos and just arbitrary appendages the
dictionary and the language improves in
quality and poetry application it begins
to embody in cultured meanings
well I'm sure that there's always more
to say and I know there's more to come
so kirtan
to the current and future ants and
humans and computers what is your
closing remark
that the world can be
a much greater more enjoyable place than
people yet imagine
and that can come in every way that
in in pretty much every way they can
enjoy it like people have their
emotional needs and they're used to
those needs not being fulfilled they're
used to coping but
the future doesn't have to be based on
coping mechanisms on addiction people
can be emotionally fulfilled they can do
what they do best they can develop their
skills without having to work themselves
to death they can
enjoy their social connections they can
expand those they can improve them they
can get assistance in making better
friends in exploring their interests in
all of the things that give us meaning
we can make all of these things better
and
that's the future that we want to bring
to the table
641 Cycles deep on stardate 2022.
thank you again for joining and we'll
look forward to the next chapter
thank you
pleasure being here and I look forward
to the next time that we catch up